<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Health on claesto</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/tags/health/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Health on claesto</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My weight loss journey</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/articles/weight-loss-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/articles/weight-loss-journey/</guid>
      <description>Insights into my weight loss journey, health and diet</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I started my weight loss journey, with hit and misses in 2021 when the scale indicated ~100kg. I&rsquo;ve dropped weight, gained again and I&rsquo;m now back on track with losing weight.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://picsum.photos/960/400"/> <figcaption>
            Weight loss graph 2021
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I achieved this result by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Applying intermittent fasting (8 hour feeding window)</li>
<li>Keto-style diet</li>
<li>PronoKal</li>
</ul>
<p>I also experimented with 48 and and even a +70 hour fasting window to provoke cell regeneration. Eventually my progress halted, and I needed to take a closer look at my daily caloric intake because simply put: more calories in than burned/consumed = fat storage</p>
<p>I made it a habit to keep track on my food intake (using YAZIO). Periods of weight loss directly correlate with my adherence to this practice of monitoring my intake and calories burned.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://picsum.photos/960/400"/> <figcaption>
            Weight loss plateau 2022 &amp; 2023
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Even though I kept bouncing back up once I reached my <em>target weight</em> of 75kg I&rsquo;m still <strong>very satisfied</strong> I managed to keep the weight off so far. According to Layne Norton, in his book &ldquo;Fat loss Forever&rdquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, only <strong>5%</strong> of people who undertake a weight loss journey actually manage to keep the weight off.</p>
<p>The main thing for me is weighing myself weekly. I switched from periods where I strictly counted calories and weighing my food to eyeballing things and trying to eat intuitively, which almost always resulted in weight gain but as soon as I started creeping back to the 80 kg mark, I was at least aware and switched back to a more rigorous routine.</p>
<h2 id="goal">Goal</h2>
<p>Allthough I&rsquo;m happy keeping the weight off, I&rsquo;m <strong>not</strong> satisfied with my current weight as I have a second goal of reaching 10% body fat. I realized that simply losing weight was not going to cut it anymore. I needed to become more intentional with my weight loss, more mindful.</p>
<p>I did some research on goal setting and realized I needed a clear target within a specific time frame, just like you need SMART objectives at work.</p>
<p>However again my weight started to creep up from 76kg to 80kg. Since my breaking point seemed to revolve around 76kg, I set a new target of 75kg within a 2 month time frame. My starting weight was 78kg and my most recent weigh-in indicated 77.2kg. So far it&rsquo;s working, losing around 0,5kg of weight a week, which is a healthy amount you can realistically lose.</p>
<p>I made a little sheet of paper and it&rsquo;s hanging on my fridge. Every day I mark with an <strong>X</strong> whether I adhered to my target of 1700kcal <em>+/- 100kcal</em>. Squares indicate a day where I do a 500kcal fasting day.</p>
<h2 id="weight-loss-interventions">Weight loss interventions</h2>
<ul>
<li>Calorie daily target: 1700kcal</li>
<li><strong>Two meals</strong> a day in a <strong>four hour</strong> eating window</li>
<li>20 hours of fasting a day</li>
<li>Tracking all calories, even when overeating</li>
<li><strong>5:2</strong> pattern week: two days of fasting a week where I eat a small meal of max. 500 kcal</li>
<li>Running 3+ times a week</li>
<li>Playing padel 2+ times a week</li>
</ul>
<p>Listed out like this, it seems <em>extreme</em> to lose only a few kilograms of fat but apparently it&rsquo;s necessary for me. When I start losing more that 0,5kg/week, I know I need to adjust my scheme by either increasing my caloric intake, or lower my activity levels.</p>
<h2 id="accountability">Accountability</h2>
<p>When I made this plan, I shared it with my wife and a few friends, including the post(s) on my website. I&rsquo;ve been on this journey alone but since I seem to get stuck at 76kg and rebounce, I upped the ante and involved others. It helps to stick with the program as it would be embarassing to make this kind of <strong>bold</strong> committment and not sticking with it.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Fat-Loss-Forever-Lose-KEEP/dp/1794510109">Fat Loss Forever: How to Lose Fat and KEEP it Off Paperback – January 21, 2019</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
