<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Zettelkasten on claesto</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/tags/zettelkasten/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Zettelkasten on claesto</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/zettelkasten/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>PARA method combined with Zettelkasten</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/articles/para-with-zettelkasten/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/articles/para-with-zettelkasten/</guid>
      <description>How I combine the PARA method to organize my digital life and Zettelkasten as my second brain.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<pre tabindex="0"><code>/organization_system
|-- Projects/
|    |-- Family trip planning/
|    |-- New homelab setup/
|    |-- Photo album/
|-- Areas/
|    |-- Family/
|    |-- Health/
|    |-- Photography/
|    |-- Finances/
|    |-- Technology/
|    |    |-- Homelab/
|    |    |-- NAS/
|    |-- Hobbies/
|         |-- Padel/
|         |-- Reading/
|-- Resources/
|    |-- Photography resources/
|    |-- Health resources/
|    |-- Padel tips and tricks/
|    |-- Technology notes/
|    |    |-- NAS guides/
|    |    |-- Homelab tutorials/
|    |-- Books to read.md
|-- Archive/
     |-- Old photoshoot project/
     |-- Homelab setup phase1/
</code></pre><h3 id="1-projects">1. Projects</h3>
<ul>
<li>Projects are short-term, actionable tasks with deadlines.
<ul>
<li>Trip planning: organize everything related to your next vacation</li>
<li>New homelab setup: track the progress of building your homelab</li>
<li>Padel tournament: prepare for upcoming tournament with. Training plans, schedules, tips, etc.</li>
<li>Photo album: a project to organize and create a family photo album</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-areas">2. Areas</h3>
<ul>
<li>Areas are ongoing areas of responsibility in your life. These don’t have a specific end date but require regular attention.
<ul>
<li>Family: general notes, tasks, or to-dos</li>
<li>Health: track your workouts, diet or personal health goals</li>
<li>Photography: Ideas, inspiration and goals for your photography hobby</li>
<li>Finances: personal finance management (budgeting, investments, etc.)</li>
<li>Technology: ongoing interests in technology Homelab and NAS</li>
<li>Hobbies: track ongoing learning in both areas</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-resources">3. Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>Reference materials or guides that don’t require action but might be useful.
<ul>
<li>Photography: books, articles, tutorials or guides</li>
<li>Padel: techniques and strategies that help improve your game</li>
<li>Health: information on fitness, recipes, or health research</li>
<li>Finance: readings on investment strategies, budgeting or other topics</li>
<li>Technology: resources for anything technology related (guides, tutotrials, etc.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-archive">4. Archive</h3>
<ul>
<li>Storing completed or inactive projects and areas. Once a project is done or an area is no longer active, move it to the archive.
<ul>
<li>Old photoshoot projects: completed or no longer relevant photography projects</li>
<li>Padel season 2023: archived training notes &amp; schedules from a past padel season</li>
<li>Homelab phase 1: once finished the first phase of setting up your homelab, you can move it here to keep it for future reference but out of your active system.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="zettelkasten-layout-personal-knowledge-managementpkm">Zettelkasten layout (personal knowledge management/PKM)</h2>
<p>The Zettelkasten would fit within the Resources section, as it’s primarily for note-taking and idea linking.</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>/Zettelkasten/
|-- 20240912_photography_how_to_frame_a_shot.md
|-- 20240913_Technology_homelab_networking_tips.md
|-- 20240914_Health_intermittent_fasting.md
|-- 20240915_Finance_CompoundInterest_Explained.md
|-- 20240916_Finance_Personal_Investment_Strategy.md
|-- 20240917_Padel_BackhandTechnique.md
</code></pre><h3 id="zettelkasten-components">Zettelkasten components:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Atomic notes: each file represents a single idea or concept. You can link related notes through hyperlinks inside your notes, creating a web of interconnected thoughts.
<ul>
<li>Example: the note 20240912_photography_how_to_frame_a_shot.md can link to other notes about photography techniques.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Timestamp: each note starts with a unique timestamp to maintain chronological order and to avoid naming conflicts. For reference, als include the Area as a keyword in your naming scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="where-to-place-your-notes">Where to place your notes</h2>
<ol>
<li>Actionable notes (e.g. to-do lists or plans) -&gt; Projects or Areas
<ol>
<li>Example: planning a trip goes into a specific Trip planning project folder</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Knowledge / reference notes (e.g. ideas from books or articles) -&gt; Zettelkasten
<ol>
<li>Example: a note on a NAS setup goes into the Zettelkasten as an atomic note, while high-level summaries or important guides go into Resources/Technology/NAS</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Ongoing reference notes (e.g. personal strategies or health data) -&gt; Areas
<ol>
<li>Example: if you’re tracking fitness progress, place logs and ideas in Areas/Health</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
<p>This combination allows for structured organization of both actionable tasks (PARA) and flexible note-taking/idea tracking (Zettelkasten).</p>
<h2 id="large-zettelkasten-folder-vs-split-by-arearesource">Large Zettelkasten folder vs. split by area/resource</h2>
<h3 id="option-1-single-large-zettelkasten-folder">Option 1: single large Zettelkasten folder</h3>
<p>All notes live here regardless of the area they belong to.</p>
<p><strong>Pros</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Flexible connections: notes are not constrained by categories, and you can freely link them based on the relationships betwen ideas, rather than their area.</li>
<li>One central place for knowledge: easy to search through a single folder without worrying about subcategories</li>
<li>Zettelkasten’s core strength: the Zettelkasten method works best when ideas are fluid, interconnected and not siloed into specific categories</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cons</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>No thematic grouping: if you have a large number oof notes, it might become hard to navigate them without specific themes or folders, even though linking can alleviate this</li>
<li>Everything mixed together: technology notes, health notes, personal finance notes could feel cluttered over time</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="option-2-zettelkasten-notes-divided-by-areas">Option 2: Zettelkasten notes divided by areas</h3>
<p>In this approach you’d have multiple Zettelkasten folders inside the Resources folder, each linked to a specific Area (like Health, Technology, Finance, etc.)</p>
<p><strong>Pros</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Thematic organization: makes it easier to focus on notes within a particular area</li>
<li>Easier for review: when looking to work in a specific area, you know exactly where to look</li>
<li>Clear separation: each area has a specific set of notes, making the structure more orderly</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cons</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Harder to link across areas: Zettelkasten thrives on cross-linking notes, and dividing them into folders discourages that, making some ideas feel artificially constrained to one area</li>
<li>More overhead: you need to decide upfront where each note belongs, and seas that span multiple areas might end up fragmented</li>
</ul>
<p>Deciding what goes in an Area vs. Resources/Zettelkasten
Here’s a general guideline for determining whether a note belongs in an Area or Resources/Zettelkasten.</p>
<h3 id="area">Area:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ongoing responsibility</strong>: Notes here are related to maintaining or managing aspects of your life (e.g., fitness goals, budget tracking, photography techniques you’re actively improving).
<ul>
<li>Example: A file detailing how you’re improving your homelab over time, with to-dos or status updates.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Applied information</strong>: Notes you’ll reference regularly as part of maintaining a long-term focus.
<ul>
<li>Example: A workout log that’s part of your ongoing health management, or a financial tracking spreadsheet.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Action-oriented</strong>: You might keep a checklist or project-related information here that informs ongoing activities.
<ul>
<li>Example: If you’re actively configuring a NAS and you have a project around it, those actionable items go in Areas/Technology.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="resourceszettelkasten">Resources/Zettelkasten:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reference material</strong>: These are static notes that you don’t act on directly but are useful for future reference.
<ul>
<li>Example: A Zettelkasten note about the best file systems for NAS storage, not tied to any specific task or project but valuable when setting up or expanding your NAS.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Knowledge capture</strong>: If a note is about learning or capturing information (rather than applying it to ongoing responsibilities), it goes in Zettelkasten.
<ul>
<li>Example: A note comparing RAID types or explaining ZFS vs. Btrfs would fit perfectly in the Zettelkasten/Technology folder, as it captures information you’ve learned.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Flexible ideas</strong>: If you’re still exploring an idea, it belongs in Zettelkasten, where it can evolve and connect to other concepts.
<ul>
<li>Example: A thought about integrating your NAS with a backup system could start in Zettelkasten as part of knowledge development and later be applied in a project.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-would-make-me-put-a-note-on-nas-in-the-area-vs-zettelkasten">What Would Make Me Put a Note on NAS in the Area vs. Zettelkasten?</h2>
<h3 id="in-an-area-eg-areastechnologyhomelab">In an Area (e.g., Areas/Technology/Homelab):</h3>
<ul>
<li>If the note is directly related to an ongoing project or active responsibility.
<ul>
<li>Example: &ldquo;Current NAS configuration and maintenance schedule&rdquo;—a detailed log of how you&rsquo;re setting up your NAS, which drives you&rsquo;re using, backup strategies, and planned upgrades. This is part of managing your homelab.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="in-resourceszettelkasten">In Resources/Zettelkasten:</h3>
<ul>
<li>If the note is knowledge-based, conceptual, or research-oriented.
<ul>
<li>Example: &ldquo;Comparison of NAS RAID configurations (RAID 5 vs. RAID 6)&quot;—this is general research on RAID types that could be useful in multiple projects or future decisions. You’re not acting on it now, but it’s useful information for whenever you revisit NAS configuration.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-personal-recommendation">My Personal Recommendation:</h2>
<p>For flexibility and ease of linking ideas, I’d suggest starting with Option 1 (a single Zettelkasten folder) inside the Resources folder. This way, your ideas remain fluid, and you can easily link concepts across areas like Technology, Health, and Finances without worrying about which folder to put them in.</p>
<ul>
<li>Why? Because Zettelkasten works best when ideas are free to interconnect, and you won’t have to think about categories while taking notes.</li>
</ul>
<p>As for Areas, reserve them for applied, active, or ongoing work (like projects and maintenance). Any knowledge that supports ongoing tasks can live in the Zettelkasten, where you can always refer to it.
This setup allows you to focus more on organizing action in Areas and leave your exploration of ideas and knowledge in Zettelkasten.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
